<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Exegesis Folder 9</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <ab>Text from http://zebrapedia.psu.edu.</ab>
            </publicationStmt>v
            <sourceDesc><ab>From Zebrapedia</ab></sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1" />
               <p><persName>Fat</persName> later developed a theory that the universe is made out of information. He started keeping a journal—had been, in fact, secretly doing so for some time. His encounter with God was all there on the pages in his—<persName>Fat</persName>'s, not God's—handwriting.</p>
        
          <p>The term "journal" is mine, not <persName>Fat</persName>'s. His term was "<title>Exegesis</title>." A theological term meaning a piece of writing that explains or interprets a portion of scripture. <persName>Fat</persName> believed that the information fired at him from time to time was holy in origin and hence a form of scripture.</p>
        
           <p>One of his paragraphs impressed me enough to copy it out and include it here.</p>
        
               <p>"Summary. (etc. —v. tractate)</p>
            
                <p><persName>Fat</persName> developed a lot of unusual theories to account for his contact with God, and the information derive there from. One in particular struck me as thought-provoking. It amounted to a kind of mental capitulation by <persName>Fat</persName> to what he was undergoing; this theory held that in actuality he </p>
            <pb n="2" />
                <p>wasn't experiencing anything at all. Sites of his brain were being selectively stimulated by tight energy-beams emanating from far off, perhaps millions of miles away. These selective brain site stimulations generated in his head the impression—for him—that he was seeing and hearing words, pictures, figures of people, in short God, or as <persName>Fat</persName> liked to call it, the Logos. But, really, he truly imagined he experienced these things. They resembled holograms. What struck me was the oddity of a lunatic discounting his hallucinations in this sophisticated manner: <persName>Fat</persName> had intellectually dealt himself out of the Game of Madness while still enjoying its sights and sounds. In effect, he no longer claimed that what he experienced was really there. Did this indicate he had begun to sober up? Hardly. Now he held the idea that 'they' or God or someone owned a long-range very tight information rich beam of energy focused on <persName>Fat</persName>'s head. In this I saw no improvement, but it did represent a change. <persName>Fat</persName></p>
            
            <pb n="3" />
                <p> could now honestly discount his hallucinations, which meant he recognized them as such. But, like <persName>Gloria</persName>, he now had a they. It seemed to me a pyrrhic victory. <persName>Fat</persName>'s life struck me as a litany of exactly that, as for example the way he had rescued <persName>Gloria</persName>.</p>
                
            <p>The <title>Exegesis</title> <persName>Fat</persName> labored on month after month struck me as a pyrrhic victory if there ever was one—in this case an attempt by a beleaguered mind, to make sense out of the inscrutable. Perhaps this is the key to mental illness: incomprehensible events occur—your life becomes a bin for hoax-like fluctuations of what used to be reality, and not only that—as if that weren't bad enough—you, like <persName>Fat</persName>, ponder forever over these fluctuations in an effort to order them into coherency. When in fact the only sense they make is the sense you impose on them, out of the necessity to restore everything into shapes and processes you can recognize.</p>
                
               <p>The first thing to depart in mental illness is the familiar </p>
                
                 <pb n="4" />
                     <p> and what takes its place is bad news because not only can you not understand it, you also cannot communicate it to the other people. The madman experiences something, but what it is or where it comes from he does not know.</p>
                
                     <p>In the midst of his shattered landscape <persName>Fat</persName> imagined God had cured him. Once you notice pyrrhic victories they seem to abound.</p>
            <p>—</p>
                     <p>Either he had seen God too soon, or he had seen him too late. In any case it had done him no good at all in terms of survival. Encountering the Living God had not helped to equip him for the tasks of ordinary endurance, which ordinary men, not so favored, handle.</p>
            <p>—</p>
            <p>Men and the world are mutually toxic to each other. But God—the true God—has penetrated both, penetrated man and penetrated the world, and sobers the landscape. But that God, the God from outside, encounters fierce opposition. Frauds—the deceptions of madness—abound, and mask themselves as their mirror opposite: pose as sanity. The masks, however, wear <gap reason="lost" unit="line"> </gap> the madness reveals itself. It is </p> 
                <pb n="5" />
                    <p>The remedy is here but so is the malady. As <persName>Fat</persName> repeats obsessively, "The Empire never ended." In a startling response to the crisis, the true God mimics the universe, the very region he has invaded: he takes on the likeness of sticks and trees and cans in gutters—he presumes to be trash discarded, debris no longer noticed. Lurking, the true God literally ambushes reality and is as well. God, in very truth, attacks and injures us, in his role as antidote. As <persName>Fat</persName> can testify to, it is a scary experience to encounter this. Thence we say, the true God is in the habit of concealing himself. 25 hundred years have passed since <persName>Heraclitus</persName> wrote, "<quote>Latent form is the Master of obvious form</quote>."</p>
                
                <p>--</p>
            <p><!-- Diagram drawn in original document --> 
                <placeName>Albemuth</placeName> <placeName>Crete</placeName> <placeName>Rome</placeName> <placeName>Calif.</placeName> x y —
                ? ? ? ? ? ? ?
                —?————————————————————————————
                </p>
                
            <p>At y, the entity including me, evolves into its ultimate state (self). The info-firing quasi-material, quasi-energy plasmate non-humanoid life form I call Zebra—from perhaps, thousands, or millions of years in the future.</p>
                
                <pb n="6" />
                    <p>By then ("y") it is virtually pure knowing, pure information [and firing it back at/to me]. It had died for the last time and no invades from "the other side" (upper realm) as well as from the future.</p>
                
            <p>This fits in with the "paranormal crisis discloses paranormal powers" and the hiding of these powers overruled by the life threatening situation: this clearly states that I possess the powers. "I know, too"—i.e. am one of them.</p>
                
                    <p>I arranged for my own <date>2-74</date> disinhibiting.</p>
                
            <p>It's not him come back from the other side but me; and once I was an Essene. But it is indeed from the other side, no longer humanoid, and it's in me now: I am right now it. "We shall see him as he really is and we shall be like him"—not him like us. This is a little different from saying, "It's ourselves in the future"; this says Zebra is specifically me.</p>
            <p>—</p>
                
                    <p><persName>Fat</persName>'s obsessive idea these days, as he worried more and more about <persName>Sherri</persName>, was that the savior would soon be in the world, he walked or would soon walk the Earth, once </p>
                
                <pb n="7" />
            <p>In <date>3-74</date> that which was in me was that which was outside me. {1} This is not the Holy Spirit; the only theology which describes this is the <persName><choice><corr>Eckhart</corr><sic>Eckehart</sic></choice></persName>-Sankara Atman-Brahman or Spark-Godhead - the division between me as microcosm (inner) and the macrocosm (outer) was abolished. This is not "theolepsy" — this is the <persName><choice><corr>Eckhart</corr><sic>Eckehart</sic></choice></persName>-Sankara concept of Moksa. God born in the person and the Godhead outside. Only my ignorance of theology has prevented me from realizing that only the <persName><choice><corr>Eckhart</corr><sic>Eckehart</sic></choice></persName>-Sankara concept can explain this experience.</p>
                
                    <p> {1} and that which was outside me was not localized (i.e. a part of reality but was the totality, viz.: cf. <persName>Xenophanes</persName>).</p>
                
                    <p>I have confused "theolepsy" with this inner-outer identity (unity) of the divine. Its holiness was indubitable.</p>
                
            <p>Via the <persName><choice><corr>Eckhart</corr><sic>Eckehart</sic></choice></persName>-Sankara route can I see how my experience could be <choice><corr>Christian</corr><sic>xtian</sic></choice> and Brahmansitic. As I correctly explained it in "<title>Valis</title>" what "Zebra" invades (in theophany) is maya—inner and outer maya.</p>
                
                     <pb n="8" />	
            <p>And I entered the "timeless total present" which <persName><choice><corr>Eckhart</corr><sic>Eckehart</sic></choice></persName> describes as the way God experiences time: all is now.</p>
                
            <p>It's interesting that my coming across this <persName><choice><corr>Eckhart</corr><sic>Eckehart</sic></choice></persName>-Sankara explanation was held back until after I finished "<title>Valis</title>"—in which (without being able to identify what happened) I depict this Moksa.</p>
                
            <p>The fact that in the writing of "<title>Valis</title>" I suddenly picked "The Friends of God"—which is correct—shows divine inspiration for the book for sure.</p>
                
            <p>Although this (my experience) is above any given religious system (as Sankara) pointed out, my acosmism (maya) points to Sankara—for me, a Sankaran <choice><corr>Christianity</corr><sic>xtianity</sic></choice>, which may be the real explanation: a melding of <choice><corr>Christianity</corr><sic>xtianity</sic></choice> and Sankarism.</p>
                
                         <p>But my contribution is seeing the rational (Christ or God) breaking through into the irrational [1] in terms of this acosmic pantheism.</p>
                
            <p>[1] and overpowering it—<persName>Spinoza</persName> to the contrary.</p>
                
                         <p>Thus I say, "There is only one rational reality: God inside us/outside: all else is irrational."</p>
                     
                <pb n="9" />
                    <p>This resembles "<title>Timaeus</title>."</p>
                    <p>Thus I state, as I do in "<title>Valis</title>," an irrational (and irreal) cosmos, into which God (the rational) breaks. This isn't ordinary pantheism or the usual concept of immanent deity.</p>
                
            <p>The only way we could see that our universe—and us—are irrational is when God the rational bursts in and we have something rational to compare the irrational with. This is my contribution to Gnosticism, <persName><choice><corr>Eckhart</corr><sic>Eckehart</sic></choice></persName>, etc.</p>
                
            <p>And I express this original—with me, from me— cosmological/theological idea fully in "<title>Valis</title>"! I've gotten away from the mere acosmism I express in earlier novels, to something worse. But I am right! I had the rational to compare it with. So "<title>Valis</title>" carries the idea of "<title><choice><corr>A Scanner Darkly</corr><sic>Scanner</sic></choice></title>" (occlusion from man to the universe). If the universe were rational, God (Zebra) would not have to invade it.</p>
                
                    <p>The clearest way the universe reveals its irrationality is that it continually contradicts itself. The irrational thus becomes the interior bulk, data including info [1] within it. [1] true rational</p>
                
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>